Citizens of Rome, gather round!
Welcome to Gordian. Now, Gordian
was famous for its knot.
And the oracle one day prophesied...
...whosoever shall untie the knot
shall conquer the entire world.
Many people came from far and wide
but no one could untie it,
until one day the
mighty Alexander arrived!
Alexander, descended from
the mighty god Apollo!
Advance!
Apollo enlightened Alexander...
...and showed him how
to untie the knot.
Sulla has returned to Rome
to establish order!
He declares that the innocent
have no reason to fear!
But that those guilty
of crimes against him...
...shall be most severely punished!
The men whose names are written
on these lists are declared outlaws!
They have no rights
as citizens henceforth...
...they may be killed on sight!
Anyone who takes it upon himself
to kill any of these men...
...will be considered
a friend of the state...
...and shall be rewarded
with the property...
...and possessions
these outlaws leave behind.
It's the greatest crime of Roman law.
Rome, 82 BC
- Mother?
- Cornelia?
Mother?
- Where's my wife?
- At her fathers.
- Grandmother, the soldiers are coming.
- Julia... stay with her.
Sulla has taken the city
with his army.
He's made lists. Hundreds
of people are on them.
- Are you?
- No, my wife's father is.
Julia stay in the house!
Don't go!
Father, where are you going?
To get your mother!
He's not on the list!
- He's the one you want to, over there!
- Where?
- Have you heard?
- Yes, we have to hurry.
What's the point running away,
might as well... die right here!
- Please go.
- She's right Cinna...
- ...you must leave now.
- Cinna!
Hurry!
Go!
Please, father.
Go, hurry!
Go!
Please, Cornelia, run!
He helped Cinna to escape!
Give me your name.
It's Caesar,
from the House of Julii.
Arrest him.
No, no! Please, no!
No! No! No!
Please, please, no!
No, please, please, no!
No, please, no!
It's in any ruler's interest
to keep peace among the people.
And the people
will only be at peace...
...if they have
a Senate representative.
Since when did the Senate
ever represent the people?
Cato, why is your mouth
hanging open?
You have nothing to fear.
You are not on my list.
Sir, if I were on your list
and if it were for the good of Rome...
...I would gladly die.
Well, when you say that,
I truly believe it to be true.
So, I repeat:
When did the Senate
ever represent the people?
I want the man with
the humblest upbringing...
...to answer me.
You?
So it's me. I will answer you.
You are all aristocrats.
Your feet have never touched the ground,
your ass has never touched a horse...
How can you possibly...
...represent the people whom
most of you have never even met!
We represent the people
by preserving their traditions.
- If they think you want to be king...
- King?
You said... king?
What would the name "King" buy me
that I don't already have?
Yeah, if the people know the Senate
is still meeting to advise you...
Oh, yes, oh, yes. Oh, they will.
That is my... fondest wish.
So,
I would not be a true Republican...
if I did not introduce a...
how do I say it?
A... earthier element...
...among your ranks
Gentlemen?
You will continue to advise me
and you will continue to debate...
...what is best
for the people, but...
...my men will remain here...
...just to make sure that
the decisions that you reach...
- ...aren't a problem.
- But, sir...
...is this not counter to Roman law?
I have just changed... Roman law.
I understand, sir.
But will something of
the old ways be preserved?
What Tallis means is,
not that we would ask you to pardon...
...anyone whom you've
resolved to destroy.
Only that it might have a calming effect
if you could make known...
...whom you intend to spare.
Oh, come, come Cato.
You know how alliances change
in troubled times.
Well, then,
perhaps you can tell us
who you intend to kill.
Well, let's...
...begin with you.
I was only asking...
...what everyone was thinking.
Well, I can't possibly kill everyone.
So, I will kill only you.
I may be true at that.
Then again I may not.
I will let you know after dinner,
but for your sake...
...you better hope
that the food is good.
- Are you Julius Caesar?
- Yes.
This way.
I want to see Sulla! Please!
No! I want to see Sulla!
I've been a member of the Senate
for thirty years!
I want to see Sulla!
Take me to Sulla!
That is not... negotiable.
Who is he?
Julius Caesar.
Nephew to Marius?
You have unfortunate ancestry.
If you think it's unfortunate
to be descendent from the gods.
Oh, which god was that?
The Julians are descendent
from Aeneas, who was...
The son of Venus,
ah, yes yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
I recall Marius making such claim.
There are many people these days
who claim to be descendent from the gods.
We have a crest which proves it.
I believe you can have them
fashioned in the marketplace for...
...a couple of dinars.
Why did you ask to see me?
Your mother...
she came to see me.
Did she... ask you to spare my life,
and what, you agreed?
Well,
I promised that
I would... consider it.
And I'm supposed
to be grateful to you?
No.
- She is. We are old friends.
- You've killed a lot of old friends.
Oh, yes, true. True, true.
Old friends in the day
become fresh enemies at night.
What do you want
in exchange for my life?
Why do you think I want
anything in exchange?
And like you don't give
things away for free.
I'm not a man without compassion.
I will help you if I can.
First you must understand
the gravity of the crime.
Cinna was my greatest enemy,
and you helped him to escape.
Did he?
Of course not.
He did escape my soldiers only
to be killed by one of his servants.
- My wife?
- She's well.
I leave women to the health.
And since you are only the son
of Cinna by marriage,
I intend to leave you to yours.
If?
If you divorce... your wife.
Well?
- No. I refuse!
- You refuse to divorce your wife...
...even though it may
cost you your life?
My wife is my teacher.
She's cleverer than I am,
she's more honest than I am,
she's a more compelling argument
than I am or you are...
...or your office is.
I won't divorce her.
- That is my answer.
- Oh, Pompey...
...what do we do
with men such as this?
I don't know weather to...
embrace him or strangle him.
I think we should let him go.
What?
His uncle Marius
was my greatest enemy.
He's got ten Mariuses inside him.
Look at his eyes.
You want to let him go?
It's the ones who smile and flatter
you should worry about.
He speaks plainly.
You do speak plainly, don't you?
Always.
Well, tell me...
...would you kill me if you could?
In an instant.
You can go.
I said you are free to go.
What a big heart that boy has.
Bring it to me in the morning.
Was this Sulla's plan?
To slaughter me outside so I wouldn't foul
the carpet with my blood?
- I came to warn you.
- Why?
Because if you don't leave Rome
I'll have to do as he asked.
And?
And I don't want to see men
like you die young.
What do you know about me?
You refused Sulla.
I'll tell you more
some day when is time,
but now you must leave Rome.
Your family will be safe,
here, take this.
Go east to Bithynia.
Show this ring to Nicomedes.
He'll keep you safe in his service.
- How do I know I can trust you?
- You don't.
I will not hand my fate
over to that man.
So you'd let him kill you?
He can try if he wants,
I'm not leaving Rome.
Why must you be so stubborn!
Pompey himself came to offer you help.
Why won't you accept it?
He's Sulla's man,
it could be a trick.
Don't you trust anyone at all?
Yes.
- I trust you.
- Then listen to me.
You're not the heaven and the earth.
You're just a man.
And some things
are bigger than you are.
When you were in jail...
...I thought you were dead.
I started to grieve your death.
I'm asking you
to spare me that, Caesar.
How can I live with myself if I knew
I had one chance to save your life,
and I failed!
- Is this pig for sale?
- How much will you give me for it?
- Ten dinars.
- That's good money for a swine.
It requires carving.
Julius Caesar.
We will feed it to my dogs.
That's the coast of Crete.
The ruler there
used to make up laws...
...and then hang them so high
that people couldn't read them.
And if they broke the law
he'd show then no mercy.
Today the shores
are infected by pirates.
We need to anchor for the night.
Where has father gone?
The other side of the water.
How long does it take
to cross the water?
Depends on the wind.
Sometimes you can cross it in days.
Sometimes if the air is still
you may not move at all.
If you don't like the rope, sir
we could use nails.
It's the Roman way, isn't it?
What kind of ransom do you get
for a Roman these days?
Two talents.
But I'll pay three
to watch a Roman drowned.
You'd get fifty for me alive.
And who would collect it?
They would.
Hey!
If your men...
...don't return before dawn...
...you die.
Your time is up, Roman.
I'll fight one of you
for another day.
That's another day.
Nobody is coming back
for this Roman.
Throw him in the sea.
Ship!
Fifty talents.
And the money just happened
to find it's way into your purse?
Sir, I never stole a coin from you.
And I suppose it was the goldsmiths
who just happened to rob me again.
- Sir, they've been convicted for it.
- I know how these things work!
You share the profits
with these men.
You pay me well, I would never
risk my life for a gold coin!
This is the magistrate's testament,
the goldsmiths have confessed.
Flavius had nothing to do with it.
Are you trying to tell me that
a man who handles so much gold,
never put a piece into his pocket?
He's been proven innocent.
This needs your signet.
- Strangle him.
- Wait!
He's been proven innocent.
Well, I just... disapprove
of the verdict.
Sulla...
...he's a good man,
and he's here on my introduction.
Allow me to vouch for him
and to protect him.
You can vouch for him all you like,
but protect him you can't.
The penalty for theft is
strangulation. Strangle him.
There seems to be
an error of judgment.
My judgment?
Pompey...
...you're becoming very critical.
And you want to rise above me.
Just are just waiting for your chance.
Those men worship the rising sun
and not the setting sun.
That's how the saying goes isn't it?
But I am not the setting sun,
not yet, and in the meantime...
...I expect you to
subordinate yourself...
...to my wishes weather
you understand them...
...or not.
Strangle him!
No.
You.
You will strangle him.
No.
Did I hear...
Did you hear him say no?
Ah, my dear general.
I asked you to strangle Flavius
and strangle Flavius you will.
And you will do it
with your own bare hands.
You will strangle Flavius...
...or you yourself
will be strangled.
Strangle him!
Strangle him now!
I will not have my orders disobeyed!
I swear to...
KINGDOM OF BITHYNIA
PROVINCE OF ASIA
...by the prince of Egypt!
Noble of stature!
Fit to serve a gentleman
such as yourself, sir!
Ah, here, sir.
This young girl, new from the North,
will have special ways
of delighting their masters,
and young enough for you
to teach her a few your own.
Oh, no. No, no, no, sir.
This... hardly able to lift
a bucket of wine unassisted.
He'll disagree
with everything you say.
He's unfortunately skilled
in the arts of the tongue.
And what arts of the tongue
are you versed?
In the arts of Euclid and Aristotle.
The arts of verse.
I can recite verse of Homer
from memory, and all of Pindar.
The arts of politics and the state.
Logic, metaphysics, epistemology
rhetoric and sophistry.
Sophistry?
Now, doesn't that mean you know
how to tell fancy lines?
There's great power in ambiguity, sir,
but not all men use advantages
to wicked ends.
Are you experienced
teaching the young?
Yes.
- I much prefer to teach in the old.
- Why is that?
Because they exhibit more wisdom.
Father.
Who are your friends?
Portia and Marcus.
Don't you remember them?
Of course, Cato's children.
Just don't grown so much.
That's our cousin.
Brutus.
- What you reading?
- "Ethics."
- Aristotle?
- My uncle Cato gave it to me.
- How is he?
- He's as grumpy as ever.
- Hasn't changed a bit.
- Mother.
Father, did you bring me
anything back from the East?
Did I bring you back anything? Yes.
I brought you this.
Apollonius?
This is my daughter Julia.
Apollonius will be your teacher.
Where's my wife?
Caesar!
- Don't get up.
- I'm not ill.
Let me get dressed.
I'm well, I just stood up too fast.
You don't have to get dressed.
Let's lie down together.
No, wait.
Just...
Cornelia.
I never stopped waiting for you.
I never stopped missing you.
And now...
Here.
This is not supposed to happen.
I'm back now, my love.
Two years is just too long.
There are those of you
who worked with Sulla,
and those of you who worked...
...against him.
But not all who worked with him
agreed with his laws.
I therefore propose that the rights
of the tribunes be restored,
so that once again the people
can be fairly represented.
Yes!
I propose a thorough
reform of the courts...
...and an unqualified
reinstatement of the Senate,
as the principal body of government.
- Yeah!
- Yes!
Caesar!
It's good to see you fresh
from another victory.
Oh, he lets me win.
It makes me feel old.
I'm glad to see
you made it back safely.
I hear you met with
a number of... obstacles.
Yes. Fortunately your friend Nicomedes
has proven to be a great ally.
I never had a chance to thank you...
...for saving my life.
You defied Sulla.
He told you to divorce
your wife and you said no...
...even though you knew
it meant certain death.
That impressed me.
And it...
...reminded me of something.
You see my friend,
Sulla once... told me
to divorce my wife.
And unlike you I obeyed him.
I left the one woman I loved.
Life is full of lessons.
So, we taught each other
a thing of two.
Tell me how to get
where you are now.
Don't tell me I was wrong
to hope you were spared.
See, I have something
to give to Rome...
...but I have no voice.
If you want a voice in Rome,
win the people,
speak from your heart...
...and when you make
a promise, keep it!
Pompey...
...I promise you
if you ever need my help...
...just give me a sign,
and I'll come to your aid.
- Man.
- Andras.
- Woman.
- Gynh.
Slave.
From memory.
Why do I have to learn Greek?
Because that is the greatest culture
the world has ever known.
- As in Rome?
- Much.
So is a Greek slave better
than a Roman free man?
I'm content to be what I am.
You can draw your own
conclusions from that.
But you'd rather be free?
All men would rather be free.
Because then you could do
what you wanted?
I can do what I want to do
even as a slave.
And some men who think they're free
are not free at all.
They're bound
by their own poor ideas.
'Cause if you're my slave
I'll set you free.
- Julia.
- Father!
If you'd set him free,
I'd have no one to educate you.
He could educate me
just the same, if he was free.
Ah, yes, but then
I couldn't afford him.
Sweet gods, come quick!
Cornelia?
Cornelia, wake up!
Oh, please, stay with me! No!
Cornelia! Please, my love!
Oh, god.
My name is Julius Caesar.
I'm here to honor
my wife, Cornelia...
...publicly and for the last time.
She was a good woman.
She gave no thought
to her own well being.
Only to the well being of others.
Rome was her first and greatest love.
We shared that love.
We dreamt of a Rome
without dictators.
Where sons never raise
their hands against fathers.
Where brothers never raise
their swords against brothers.
Where Romans lived at peace
with their fellow Romans by their side.
So I ask you now to join with me,
in honoring not only
the memory of my good wife,
but the memory of all
good men and women...
...who have died fighting
for a better Rome.
People of Rome, I, Julius Caesar,
make you this promise
on the body of my beloved wife:
I will not rest till the Rome
she dreamed of is the Rome we live in.
Join me!
For I am not only the nephew
to our beloved Marius,
who fought against the evils of Sulla
until Sulla took his life from him,
but I'm also a son of the Julius,
who was descended from
the goddess Venus herself.
I offer you my hand.
A power supreme among mortal men,
granted by the gods,
superior to kings!
Let us work together comrades,
in our quest for an empire,
that is boundless,
united...
...and free!
We shall have to watch him.
Or use him.
Good morning to you, Caesar.
- Good morning.
- Caesar!
Hail, Caesar!
Greetings, Caesar!
Greetings, Caesar.
Hey, Julia, I have something for you.
Now, then... Ah, here!
And I hope it will make you smile.
That's the first
I've seen you smile in weeks.
Stop it all of you!
There is nothing he can do about it!
What happened?
The price of bread is tripled.
- There's no grain in Rome.
- Why?
Because the grain supply from Egypt
was cut off by pirates.
Half Rome is without bread.
The city is close to panic.
Only the very rich can afford bread.
We must fight the pirates now
or Rome will be crippled forever.
So I propose that Pompey be given legions
to attack this problem...
...once and for all.
It's not a question of whether
or not we fight pirates,
it's a matter of how.
I propose we equip ten small armies...
...to fight the pirates
at different parts of the coast.
But the pirates can destroy Rome,
you want to buy time?
The pirates are a bunch
of uneducated hoodlums.
I hardly think they could withstand
a Roman assault of any size.
Let's talk about the way
things are gentlemen.
Not about the way
we'd like then to be.
I can attest to the threat posed
by these scavengers.
I was a victim of one
of their assaults myself.
Then perhaps you will regale us
with your sea stories Gaius Julius,
in the tavern after the work
of the Senate is done.
The work of the Senate
is rarely done.
You see there are not
thousands of pirates...
...in our waters,
but hundreds of thousands.
And not all the rogue bands
preying on single vessels.
There are pirate admirals, sea kings...
...with thousands of ships
and troops more skilled...
...in the naval combat
even than our own.
Pretty speeches like this
won't even cook our lunch!
No, speeches do as little
work as the Senate.
How dare this arrogant newcomer
insult this August body?
August and plump, Bibulus,
like your own body.
Fat from idle
chatter and inactivity.
Enough, enough... Enough!
We have a man in
our company who can...
...resolve this conflict
with the pirates.
But do we honor him
with that duty?
- No.
- I'm with Caesar...
...we have no bread.
Now are we a great empire or...
...are we going
to be ruled by outlaws?
To perform this commission,
Pompey will have to be given
an army twice the size...
...of the one Sulla used
to take Rome.
Have we learned
nothing from the past?
I see.
Rome should go hungry because Cato
can't find a single man he can trust.
Not any man with an army
would take the state.
Not every man is a Sulla.
Some men are ruled by circumstance
but men of character...
...bend circumstances to their will.
They make nature
behave in such a way...
...that their will is carried out
on this earth.
They defy the elements,
and sometimes even defy
their own baser nature,
in order to see that their ideals...
...come alive before their eyes.
Pompey is such a man.
Those of you who have lived...
...know that one thing alone
keeps the nation small.
Civil strife.
Tribes fighting tribes rather than
banding together...
...in one arm of power.
As long as we fight in this room...
...seeking personal victories,
enacting petty revenges,
Rome will stay small!
I propose we put our opinions aside...
...and let one feeling
rule us for a time:
The love of Rome.
I propose we put our strengths
together to become a force...
...the world has never seen.
I propose we let a man...
...a single man,
lead us out of the dark.
I propose Pompey.
All those in favor.
Can we come inside?
You said me we could.
Why, there's nothing but a bunch
of dusty old senators in here.
Is the consul in there?
Yes, this is consul Gnaeus Pompey.
And who is this?
This is my daughter Julia.
And Apollonius,
the wisdom of our household.
Julia, your father has just proved to us
he'll have my job one day.
- But don't think it's all fun.
- Why?
Because he'll always have
these men around him.
They're silly looking old men.
I'll see when I return.
In triumph.
Apollonius says...
...that when we die, our soul goes
to a place where everything is perfect.
All the beds are perfect beds,
all the circles are perfectly round.
YEARS LATER
- Marcus!
- Julia.
Julia... look at you.
Brutus, wake up and tell Julia
how beautiful she looks.
- Beautiful.
- Do you like it?
All dressed for Pompey's triumph.
Has Apollonius returned?
I wanted to talk to him about Plato.
No, he hasn't returned.
I'll bet he ran off to fight
with the rebel slaves.
Those rebel slaves
are not like Apollonius.
They aren't educated men
with happy homes.
Well, we had a Moorish cook
who ran off a month ago.
We heard he joined the rebels,
and that was made commander.
From cook to commander,
it's so inspiring!
You talk as if it's a game.
I don't.
Think about it.
At least half of the population of Rome
is made up of slaves.
And what would happen
if they all decided to rebel?
It would be the end of Rome.
Rome had to act.
What do you mean?
Pompey... he defeated 20,000 of them
on his way back to Rome.
I was going with you.
None of you wants to join
the consul of Rome?
No offense, father,
but do you really think...
...we're going to trail along
with your lectors around.
Rome's greatest general returns and...
we want to be free to run...
- ...and follow him.
- Run, yes. Run, run.
Go, enjoy yourselves.
- Come on.
- Thank you Consul.
Brutus?
Aren't you going with them?
- I wanted to return this to Apollonius.
- What's this?
Ah, yes, Plato's Law.
- Did you read it?
- Yes.
And?
Well, Plato thinks that democracy
is doomed to failure.
He thinks that a state
should be run by a dictator.
A dictator who's become enlightened
through experience and learning.
I don't think Plato would get along
very well with your uncle Cato.
- Brutus! Hurry up!
- Come on!
Hurry and catch up with your friends
or you'll have to come along with me.
- See you at the ceremony.
- Hurry up!
Goodbye, father!
Pompey! Pompey! Pompey! Pompey!
Thank you for your kindness.
Let me take care of my son now.
Who are these people?
- Prisoners.
- Pirates?
Pirates and slaves.
Rebellious slaves.
Apollonius! Apollonius!
Apollonius!
Consul! Consul!
Step back!
Wait.
Speak.
I have a friend among
the slave prisoners.
I ask you... to free him.
And who are you
to deserve such favor?
I'm Julia, daughter of
Gaius Julius Caesar.
- Your fellow consul.
- The consul's daughter?
Didn't you know,
that those who choose to fight...
...against Rome are Rome's enemies,
and will be crucified tomorrow?
Apollonius was my teacher
not an enemy of Rome!
Everything good and decent
I have ever learned...
...has been taught to me by him.
You must spare him!
For my sake!
Consider your wish granted.
Take her to the holding pens,
and release this slave Apollonius
into the custody of his lawful owners.
Yes, sir.
Thank you, Consul.
Thank you.
- Apollonius!
- It's Julia?
Apollonius...
...I've come to take you home!
I'm not coming with you.
I shall stay here.
They will crucify you!
You've grown into a fine woman.
Intelligent,
full of everything that makes
the Romans great.
I am not a Roman, Julia.
- I am a slave.
- You're not a slave any longer.
You're free!
I am freeing you know!
Freedom is not something
you can be given.
It's something you have to take.
If you have done it earlier,
you could have been free years ago.
I should have asked my father.
He would have granted it.
But I never thought
it would make a difference.
It felt as though you were free.
I thought you happy.
I was.
But isn't happiness I'm seeking out.
- Something else.
- What?
Dignity.
You've been good to me.
You've been my family.
But they are my family now.
We both know where we belong...
...and I belong in there, with them.
One day you'll understand...
...my dear Julia.
Goodbye.
Mother...
Rest.
Something happened to me there.
It's an affliction, no more no less.
Your grandfather suffered
the same spells and lived into old age.
I meant something else.
Thought it happened
when I was watching Pompey.
He's been a friend to me,
and we speak together easily...
like brothers.
Yet we couldn't be more different.
He's a great army leader.
His provinces make him the richest
and most powerful man in Rome.
Your father wanted you to be a statesman
and now you are a consul of Rome.
That would have been
beyond his dreams.
I need an army.
To turn yourself into a Pompey?
How would you pay and feed
such an army?
Your consulship
already cost a fortune.
Yes, I am consul and I am broke.
The attack today
was stronger than usual.
There was something else mother,
this attack was different
in other ways.
How?
I saw something.
I saw something at that moment.
Not just about myself...
...but about the whole humankind.
How we keep ourselves small.
And I realized
I have not been inspired.
And as I watched Pompey
I saw that he was not inspired,
and he would never be inspired.
And I realized the difference
between Pompey and me.
Pompey has merely done something...
...but I am for something.
And I need legions.
Pompey has them.
He will lend them to me.
Why would Pompey do that,
diminishing his own power?
What could you offer him in return
equal as the value of an army?
Julia...
...I'm sorry for
what happened to Apollonius.
I felt great affection
for him as well.
We trust in the wisdom
of our forefathers,
and in their laws.
And I, Cato, trust in him.
Hail Pompey!
Cato, you flatter me.
But let us give credit
to another man!
For I could not have fought
a war across the sea...
...without knowledge that Rome
was in safe hands here at home.
And for that we owe a debt of gratitude
to my friend and fellow consul,
Gaius Julius Caesar!
Hail, Caesar!
This is my daughter, Julia.
Yes I know, we've met.
It would honor my house
if you would give us a recitation.
Not in front of so many people.
You've done it in
larger groups than this.
Father, I assure you
that I'm not prepared for it.
Come. Come.
The daughter of Caesar
will recite for us!
Tonight,
stand beside me and praise with me...
...a man dear to me and to the gods.
Mightier in victory
than the kings of Mycenae,
with their golden haired horses.
And stronger far more
than the battle ghosts,
that ride the shores of Troy.
Hear me,
sons of gold headed men.
Hear me sing the victory...
...of a man dear to me
and to the gods.
- It's really nothing.
- No, it's not your fault.
I'm not sure whose fault it is
but I assure you I will find out,
and he will be punished severely.
Thank you, Consul, you're very kind.
- What's your name?
- Calpurnia.
- From which House?
- Lucius Piso.
I'm sorry for staring,
I thought perhaps we...
...met somewhere before.
- Would you like to eat together?
- I'd be delighted.
What hour do you call this?
I think it's known
as the fifth hour.
Yes, the sun is coming up.
You're right, I was out with him.
We drank and ate
and had entertainment.
- He cares for me.
- Oh, yes, he's twice your age.
And your friend, remember?
Yes, he is my friend.
I just want to know
if he treats you with respect.
I like him. I do.
I don't love him, not yet, but...
...that may come.
Why are you behaving
in such a manner?
He is consul.
He is the first man in Rome.
He has legions.
The price is high.
Price? It's customary for
the father to offer a dowry.
You know I have nothing to give you.
I accept.
I want a commission.
Gaul.
- Gaul? It's taken.
By Cassius.
- I need a victory in battle.
You're not experienced enough
in warfare and you need legions!
Your legions.
She's all I've got,
I want 50,000 for her.
Talents?
Soldiers.
How could you do it?
How could you take my commission away?
Because I think Caesar's
the right man for Gaul.
But I've already put myself to considerable
expense preparing my men.
- And you'll be reimbursed.
- What?
And I'll propose that you
look after the garrison.
- The garrison?
- This won't do, Pompey.
- You didn't put this before the Senate...
- Let's not talk business...
...at my wedding.
It may tempt bad luck.
I have a confession to make.
What's that?
We did meet before. Or rather...
...I met you,
but you didn't meet me.
It was at Pompey's triumph.
You fell.
Nobody saw it, but me.
I held you to make sure you didn't...
- ...hurt yourself.
- Thank you.
It shames me.
I never know when
it's going to happen.
Many people believe that
those who have the condition...
...are holy.
Blessed by the gods.
Perhaps.
What do you suppose
a child of both of our faces...
...blended together
would look like?
I think... it would look
rather beautiful.
Do you?
- Is it something you'd like to find out?
- Yes.
Are you sure?
I am less sure about my own name
than I am about this.
I am terrible around the house.
We have servants.
I'm not one for parties,
I go to bed early.
I'll follow you.
Caesar...
- ...you must make me a promise.
- Anything you like.
Come back from this war alive.
I promise you.
- And hurry.
- That's two promises.
- And win it.
- Now, that's three promises.
Now it is your turn
to promise me one thing.
Will you marry me before I leave?
BORDERS OF GAUL
58 B.C.
- How many dead?
- In the region of 23,000 Celts.
- And Romans?
- 112.
I've had to prepare
the burial back in Rome.
We're not returning to Rome.
We're going farther north.
There's a lot more of Rome out there.
Just isn't called Rome yet.
The Rome attacking!
We must tell Caesar to retreat.
What I gave to Caesar,
I will not revoke.
Wait!
Put down your blades.
Why have you come here?
This land is ours,
you have no right to be here!
What is your name?
Vercingetorix.
- You stayed to fight alone?
- This is my house.
I'll fill it with my own hands,
if you burn it down!
You're free to go.
Give me a horse.
You heard him.
Give him a horse.
My dear Caesar,
the people speak of you
with admiration.
Some call you "the Great"
as they called Pompey.
In the market, people sometimes
bow to me as I pass.
It will also delight you to know,
that the marriage that began
as an advantage,
has blossomed into romance.
Watching Julia and Pompey
together delights me,
and saddens me
that you're not here.
No one could be prouder
to be your wife, Caesar.
But after so long without you,
I fear I'm getting used
to my solitude.
Come home soon my darling.
Until then I will be waiting.
Caesar has killed 300,000 Celts!
He attacked peaceful villages,
villages who pay taxes to the Roman state!
It's beyond toleration!
This is how you thank
a great Roman general?
Caesar sent 100,000 slaves
back to Rome!
Are you saying you haven't
taken any of them?
Oh, if they hadn't come from him,
I would have got them
from somewhere else.
Pompey, you have to be weary.
He's been away three years
fighting with your legions.
He's doubled their salary.
They are totally devoted to him!
My lords, as Cicero
has put it so well:
Strain every nerve for
the preservation of the state,
look in every corner for the storms.
They will burst upon you
if you do not see them in time.
I just remembered who he is!
- What are you talking about?
- That man!
- Mark Antony?
- Yes!
Running from his debtors in Rome
to find wealth in the province...
- ...like all of us.
- Hey, not me!
I still fight for the glory of Rome!
- Our cavalry's been attacked.
- By who?
- Gallic tribesmen. 14,000 dead.
- 14,000?
And many more wounded.
They've united under one leader.
His name is Vercingetorix.
- Where could we find him?
- In Alesia.
- How long is the march?
- Eight days.
Vercingetorix is in there
with 18,000 of his men.
It's the most invincible
stronghold in Gaul.
- We'll never break it.
- Well, we won't have to break it.
We'll build a wall
around their city.
We'll trap them inside
and starve them.
Nobody's ever built
a fortification of that length.
Then we will be the first.
Let's not waste time.
What do you mean?
- I'm here to see Pompey.
- This way.
POMPEY'S MANOR
Pisa
- Cato!
- Pompey.
Julia!
What brings you to Pisa?
I've come to speak with you.
Your absence in Rome
has been... criticized.
As you can see,
my wife needs me here.
Could we speak privately?
What's the matter, Cato?
Did your conversation
depend on speaking ill of my father?
Sit, sit, Cato.
Thank you.
Caesar is about to take
the last stronghold in Gaul,
Vercingetorix has called forth every tribe
from the mountains to the sea!
They are on the move to Alesia!
How many men?
Two hundred and fifty thousand!
- And my husband?
- Forty thousand.
He... He will survive. He has survived
these many years.
He's never been up against so much.
Is this true?
Will my husband lose this time?
No one knows the outcome of war.
You are consul.
Pompey, do something.
If Caesar wins this battle...
He will become the next Sulla.
That's what you were going
to say, wasn't it?
That if he wins he will
become the next Sulla.
Why are you worried, Cato?
You said he doesn't stand a chance
against the Gauls.
Why call him back?
Why not just leave him there to fight
this battle to his own death?
If you leave him there, your next Sulla
will extinguish himself.
You're waiting for my husband
to fail, aren't you?
And so are you.
My dear Calpurnia,
I'm doing everything in my power
to make sure I come home safely to you.
You must have heard we've built a wall
to hold the Alessians in.
What you may not know is that
we've built a second wall as well...
...to keep their allies out.
I say this to reassure you...
...they can round up ten times our number
and still we will defeat them,
because it's not numbers
but vision that wins wars.
My vision is of
returning to you, my love.
And not just returning,
but returning victorious...
...as I've promised you.
When my men are tired,
I can't always let them rest.
When they're hungry,
I can't always feed them.
But when they forget their vision,
I can share mine with them.
And the more that I share...
...more of it I have.
It will take 30 days
to round up the tribes.
How much food have we got?
27 days of grain.
Then we'll make them last 35.
We will divide rations...
...of all the grain
brought to the stores.
With the penalty of death,
no one will eat beyond their measure.
The tribesmen come from
the countryside to fight with us.
The Gauls will outnumber
the Romans five to one.
If we succeed...
...we could destroy the Roman
presence in Gaul forever.
If we fail... we'll be their slaves.
In the evening we take our leisure.
Tell stories about the city
and our families,
or just eat in silence
after our hard day's work.
The men do work hard,
but, there are worse things
than hard labor.
Waiting is much worse.
Waiting is the hardest
part of war, my dear wife.
Most of our men would welcome
the cry of battle...
...over this dreaded silence.
They would fight an enemy
we could see however great...
...sooner than fight the one in our minds
which goes on killing forever.
The real enemy is almost a comfort...
...I sometimes think
as I look up the hill to Alesia.
They're just like us,
they have courage like us,
they're dying like us.
The tribe should have been
here by now.
If they don't come...
...we'll have to fight on our own.
We don't have enough men.
I say...
- ...we give ourselves up.
- And be Roman slaves?
If we die... our gods die.
At least if we live...
- In slavery?
- In any state.
If we live, we can perform
that service to the gods.
We can keep them living
for our children.
You think the gods would want us
to keep them alive...
...so they can be
worshipped by slaves?
If we have nothing
left to feed ourselves with,
I say we... do what our
ancestors did:
We eat the elderly and the infirm...
...to keep ourselves alive.
We won't eat our own people.
There's enough food left
for several days...
...if we only feed our men.
There's a way we can
compromise the Romans.
To weaken them.
They say...
...we give up our women
and children to them.
Our rations will keep us alive
for several more days.
If our women and children
become their slaves...
...the Romans
will have to feed them...
...and that will deplete
their supplies.
We must bid farewell
to our families.
We must do it today...
...and whatever happens you must
lock the gates behind them forever.
Our survival depends upon it.
This will be our sacrifice
to the gods.
Open the doors!
Please, help!
Open the gates!
Send men down to the gates.
Bolt the gates...
...and double the guard.
Caesar,
I beg you to reconsider.
They'll all die.
I will not stare my own men...
...to keep the enemy alive.
Send them back to Alesia.
Go back!
Go!
Open the gates!
- What is this?
- A soup.
This is not soup.
This is water!
We fight for years,
and they give us water!
We die for Rome, and we get water?
Stop! Now!
What is the difference between
the Romans and the Gauls?
Discipline!
We act as one body!
That's what makes us strong!
You think I eat well...
while you starve?
I eat the same portions as you...
...and I am hungry.
But I would eat soil, before I give up
what we've come here to get!
And that is everything...
...you see!
You!
Will you raise your family...
...on that hillside?
Would that be a plot of land?
You!
That field there...
...between those trees...
...that's yours if you want it.
It's rich soil, good for growing.
All of you...
...each and every one of you
will get his share!
You have worked for it.
By the gods, we've given our souls
to this place for eight years!
Let's not abandon
before we get them back!
Open the gates!
I told you before, and I tell you again,
is the worst Caesar's crime!
He's away in war on behalf of Rome!
- We commissioned him to fight the Gauls!
- Not all of them!
He started fighting the insurgents
at the borders and moved on...
...to murder...
...peaceful Roman allies, Gauls,
who pay taxes and tribute to Rome.
I fear the gods gentlemen!
Caesar is not Sulla,
he's not fighting the Romans,
he's fighting the Gauls!
He's not threatening us,
we are threatening him!
Once Caesar was consul, how many times
did he push through a law...
...without having it ratified?
He has no respect for us!
Something had better be done...
...and right away!
I propose we do nothing at all.
Cassius.
You say all of Gaul
is rallying against him?
He can't possibly win...
against such numbers.
To arms!
This is it.
Motion at the gate!
He's trying to fool us
into gathering our troops here.
How do you know what he'll do?
Because it's what I would do.
I will wait here for
Vercingetorix to make his move.
His men are too weak
to attack our main camp.
He will move his cavalry here and try
to break through the inner wall...
...while his allies attack
from the outside.
We cannot let these
two forces join together.
If they do, we will not survive.
Prepare to fire!
Fire!
Forward!
We must hold on!
Go!
Retreat!
Try one! Try the other!
Caesar, your men are asking for you.
It is with great sadness that I write
this letter to you, my dear husband.
Your Julia gave birth early and
she suffered some pain in doing so.
The doctors were there and did
what they could to ease her suffering.
The child was a boy, but frail,
their efforts could not save him.
He looked like you, Caesar,
there was nobility in his face.
Your daughter struggled
to sustain this tragic birth,
but in the end she could not.
Pompey has kept himself
from the Senate,
preferring instead
to pass time in no company.
He walks around the graveyard
again and again,
keeping fresh garlands on her tomb.
We take Alesia in the morning.
Open the gate!
I know your only real enemy is one man
and he is standing before you now.
I'm giving myself to you, Caesar.
Our women died for us.
I give you my own life
so that you may let my men live.
If my men die, there will be
nothing left of the Gauls,
no one left
to worship our gods.
I beg you.
Enslave my people if you need to,
but let them live.
Your men will live.
My dear wife,
we will have to wait a bit more
before we're together again.
You see there are those in Rome
who would have me branded an outlaw.
So I have sent Mark Antony to talk
to the Senate on my behalf.
Since there has never been a soldier
with an army such as mine...
...who returned to Rome
without taking her by force,
I too must be planning such an assault,
but my crime is worse.
Because I return not
in dishonor, but in triumph.
And this the Senate cannot tolerate.
How long ago did Sulla
ride in the town with his army,
breaking the sacred
Roman law stating that no man...
...must bring armed men
past the Rubicon into Rome?
How fresh in your memory does bloodshed
have to be, for you to show caution?
Caesar has done more for Rome
than any other general in its history.
How do you respond?
You strip him of his consulship,
in his absence, without explanation.
He's more than doubled the size of Rome
in the last eight years...
...and what do you ask him to do?
Lay down his arms.
It is not Caesar,
who is the criminal.
It is this Senate!
This Senate represents
the people of Rome.
its own interests.
Sulla said almost the very same thing.
If he said it, he was right.
But the difference between
Sulla and Caesar is:
The people feared Sulla,
Caesar they love.
You know nothing...
...of the people's feelings.
You're right, I don't.
Let me ask them.
People of Rome, I come to you
with questions from Caesar!
He needs to know what you want
so he can better serve your needs.
The Senate says
they represent the people,
but the Senate wants Caesar to lay down
his arms, and return to Rome as a man,
not as a soldier.
And when he arrives, the Senate...
...will find him guilty
of crimes against the state.
Caesar's crime is spending
eight years in battle, outside of Rome,
with none of the comforts
we all take for granted...
...and with a daily threat
to his life. Why?
So he can bring wealth
to the Roman people.
Temples, libraries,
holidays and games...
...are all funded
by Cesar's levies in Gaul,
yet what do they think in the Senate?
They think he's doing this
for personal gain. I ask you:
If he's doing this for private gain,
why does he stay in Gaul?
Why does he live in a tent?
I know why he does it.
He does it so we Romans
can live well.
What are you going to do about this?
Whatever these men may think,
some of whom have never been
up on a horse's back,
I have never known a man
tougher on the enemies of Rome,
nor gentler to its friends.
When I call myself a Roman,
the thing that makes me most proud,
is to share that title
with one other man!
A man whom it has been
my privilege to fight beside,
a man who has shown
time and again...
...that he loves his own life
less than he loves yours!
His name is Gaius Julius Caesar!
Caesar!
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
We must do something, Pompey.
Caesar could march
on Rome at any time.
I'm not going to wait for him
to come to us.
I'll gather our troops...
...and attack him before
he sets foot in Rome.
I'm going to wipe him and his legions
off the face of the earth.
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
Men, we have two choices:
We can be slaughtered by the army
Pompey is amassing against us,
or we can fight for our lives,
just as we've done
every day for eight years!
I've made my decision!
I'm going to Rome!
I'm going to cross the Rubicon!
Will anyone be coming with me?
Yeah!
To Rome! Let the dice fly!
My legions from Spain should
sail to Ostia from the West.
The Thracians will come to us
from the North,
and from the East the Macedonians.
Caesar is on his way to Rome!
- How far is he?
- Four days from here.
That's impossible!
I heard it from Bibulus himself.
Caesar has passed the Rubicon.
We must leave Rome.
We cannot defend it without troops.
We'll go to Greece.
We amass what strength we can,
and then we take him in Rome itself.
I only hope we don't
arrive too late...
...and find the bodies of
our friends on the Senate steps!
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
It has been decreed
by the new Senate...
...that the title of dictator
is bestowed upon Gaius Julius Caesar.
It has been decreed...
...there will be fifty days
of thanksgiving in his honor.
He is given the courts
and elected consul for life.
Hail, Caesar!
You treat me as a king,
though I assure that is
one role I shall never adopt.
I am Caesar, and only Caesar.
Is for this crown alone
that I conquered Gaul.
Caesar!
Beware the Ides of March!
The Ides of March...
...beware!
The men and women of Rome
are crying out for your head.
For a moment,
I saw them as you do.
You don't know how I see them.
I was disgusted with them.
How do you keep your purpose
clear in your mind?
When I met you in
your village, I could see...
...that you had your purpose
clear in your mind,
and it was pure.
I can see that it hasn't changed.
What did you do to preserve it?
You want to know?
Yes.
I only fight my enemies.
You think we are similar, don't you?
That's why it pains you
to see me die.
But we are very different, you and me.
I know when it's over.
Or when what's left
isn't worth having.
Give me the honor of dying alone...
...by my own hand,
instead of in a public spectacle
for your Roman mob.
I have to do what the people want,
I have no choice.
I thought power gave you
more choice, not less.
Listen to them! Do you hear that?
I don't hear anything
anymore but the voices...
...of our women and
our children in Alesia.
I can hear them when I'm asleep...
...and I hear them when I'm awake.
For pity's sake, give me a sword.
Hail, Caesar!
The ranks here...
- ...are depleted.
- My men will be joining you.
How shall we explain to the people...
...that these men
have become senators?
They haven't been selected...
- ...by the traditional legal...
- The law is changed!
And keep in mind,
the people trust my judgment.
And you will be joined
by my finest men.
I've spent eight years
with them in Gaul.
I must leave for Greece
to fight Pompey.
I'm leaving Rome in
Mark Antony's capable charge.
Do we have no say in this?
I don't want to distract you
with bureaucracy.
I'd rather leave you free
to argue matters of the state!
Do you think there will be black lists?
There won't be any lists.
Sulla killed his enemies,
I forgive mine.
Good day to you, gentlemen.
They left in a hurry.
Attend the Caesar!
I did not cross the Rubicon
to kill old friends.
I did it to protect myself
against my enemies.
I'm hoping we can secure ourselves
through mercy and not through vengefulness.
You're all free to go.
We owe all our lives to Caesar.
Did you say something,
my old friend?
I thought I heard you speak.
I'm grateful for your clemency.
Brutus, come dine with me.
Caesar...
...make peace with Pompey.
Now, for years, his only hope
was that one day,
you would rule Rome,
together again...
- ...with...
- With what?
With Julia, uniting you both.
Yes, he tolerated me,
because he loved Julia so much.
Caesar, he loved Julia
because he saw you in her.
He told me that... Julia's death
was almost unbearable.
And add to that the end of your friendship,
he counted his life as finished.
I'll make peace with him
if peace is what he wants.
I want to establish
some sanity in Rome.
The people have had
enough of fighting.
Will you help me?
How can I help you?
I want you to go back to Rome
and be my Praetor.
If peace is what you want,
then it'll be my honor to serve you.
Pompey has gone to Egypt.
The king died, leaving throne
to be squabbled over...
...by a twelve-year-old boy
and an eighteen-year-old girl.
Ptolemy and Cleopatra?
I don't know which one I trust less.
Help me ready the ships.
I'll follow him in the morning.
You don't need to take
troops with you.
Pompey has gone to Egypt alone.
The troops went to Utica.
- With your uncle Cato?
- Yes.
Trust me, Brutus,
whoever wants peace, will have it.
ALEXANDRIA
Egypt
He was most cruelly murdered
on the palace steps by his own men, sir.
It has been rumored that they were
bribed by Pothinus.
By Caesar.
There's only one enemy left.
I am Pothinus,
chief of the ruling council.
In the name of king Ptolemy,
I welcome you, Caesar.
Your king is very generous,
but as you can see,
we haven't brought any horses.
This grain is for your men, sir.
My men will eat indoors, Pothinus.
I'm sure you'll put us up
very comfortably... in your palace.
I'll tell you the truth, Caesar.
Ptolemy fears for his life.
There's been a great deal
of discord in Egypt,
so he has forbidden all visitors.
You, of course,
are very welcome in the palace.
And my men?
And your men.
Pothinus,
you wouldn't have
anything to do with...
...helping the king make his decisions?
- Would you?
- The king is a boy, sir.
Forgive him, and forgive me.
We are your allies and
your servants, great Caesar.
We only have the interests
of Rome in our hearts.
Bring out the gift.
This is Pompey's ring!
Where is he?
We thought...
...you'd be pleased.
Excuse me, Caesar.
There's a servant with an urgent
message from Cleopatra.
Bring her!
If you want to hear the message
you'll have to dismiss your guard.
What word from Cleopatra is
of such importance?
Cleopatra asks for your protection.
Protection, why?
Pothinus plans to kill her,
as he did Pompey.
Is that why you are disguised
as your own servant...
...Cleopatra?
I came to you, Caesar,
because you are
the only man I can trust.
Why does Pothinus want to kill you?
My father wanted me to rule Egypt,
he wrote it in his will.
But Pothinus banished me
with a price on my head.
Now any servant can kill me
and be rewarded for it.
Caesar...
...you and I, are alike.
You are the son of Venus,
and I am the daughter of Isis.
You and I, live by the same divine...
...heartbeat.
That's why we must
help each other.
Are you trying to seduce me?
I don't try.
I seduce...
...or I don't.
I do not have to seduce
with my body.
I have something
much better than that:
My country.
It is the richest
land in the world.
Egypt and Rome are different.
Rome is masculine,
Egypt is feminine.
Rome, is sunlight, Egypt is twilight.
But it's not part of Rome, not yet.
Make me queen, and the East
and West will be united.
We will be god and goddess
ruling the world.
You kiss me with
the tongue of a serpent.
I must test you to see
if you are poison.
- And am I?
- No, but I can taste Gaul.
- Will you stay with in Egypt, Caesar?
- What does Egypt have to offer...
- ...that Rome does not?
- Have you heard of the fertile crescent?
- Is it a region down below?
- Indeed it is!
What grows there?
I believe the region
fertile enough to hut a king.
If you doubt it, try planting
something there!
Only promise me one thing.
When you return to Rome,
you must be fateful to me.
But I'm married,
I'm already being unfaithful...
- ...with you!
- Let's go.
Demand you give yourself to a woman.
In politics you lie,
like serpent!
You think that her influence is evil.
And no one is more
ambitious than she is.
And she'll do anything
to achieve her ends.
Some say she's a witch.
I think you've been skulking
too long in the dark.
If Caesar wants to be king...
- ...would you prevent it?
- He doesn't want the crown!
What if he did?
Of course I'd do anything
to keep the Kings out of Rome.
At least with Sulla, the Tyranny
ended with his death.
With a king...
...the reign can be
passed on to his son...
...to another son forever.
Our ancestors knew too well
what that was like.
Had your ancestors fought to sent the Kings
outside the city gates,
they would stop at nothing
to free Rome from them.
So would I.
That's what we hoped
to hear you say.
Is this just conjecture?
I've heard nothing about this
except from you.
They were all talking it about, Brutus.
They say there's nothing between
him and the crown but Cato your uncle.
Cesar promised me...
...that he would never kill Cato.
Do you think Cesar's incapable
of breaking a promise?
Is it worth trying him
in a matter of such urgency?
If Cato is killed
and Caesar wants the crown...
...then I'll be the first to oppose it.
But I will not prepare myself
against him... until there's proof!
CATO'S FORT
UTICA, NORTH AFRICA - 46 B.C.
- Father!
- Where's my sword?
- I had it removed.
- Why?
You said before that
if Caesar won the battle...
- ...you might...
- My own son...
...would deliver me naked
to the arms of my enemy.
Your own son wants you to live!
So, you take away the sword
you take away the choice.
When did I go mad that you have
to take choices from me...
...for my own protection!
Am I your father or your son?
Why don't you bind
my hands as well...
...so I can't defend myself at all?
- We'll bury him with honors.
- I'll bury him myself.
Let the state celebrate his life.
Which state? Rome?
The Rome of Caesar?
To accept your honors
would defile my name.
And on behalf of
my father and my family,
I decline.
Now I'm asking you
to leave this room.
We should speak of Cato as a god.
He killed himself so he
wouldn't be brought down...
...by the hand of
the lesser man... Caesar.
The higher we lift Cato's name...
...the lower Caesar's will sink.
Still... we must appear
to be rallying support.
No.
No, it's an art to plant ideas
in the heads of others.
And a man is never so resolved as it is
when he thinks a conviction is his own.
That's why we need
Brutus on our side.
It wouldn't be mixed in with the cause
if it burned the good one.
They listen to him.
What if he won't...
mix in with our cause?
I think I know how to soften Brutus...
...but I will need your help.
There is no peace in the world
like in my house.
Calpurnia...
...would you greet
your husband with a kiss?
Dismiss them.
Can't a man return to his home and expect
a warmer mood from his wife?
How could you bring her to Rome?
It was for the good of the state.
Cleopatra rules
a large part of Africa.
And all of you.
No one rules me, Calpurnia.
Not Cleopatra, not even you.
But what I want is the love that
you promised me when we married.
You can't have it.
You can have my obedience,
you can have my loyalty,
but I cannot love
those who dishonor me.
No one can dishonor you.
You're right, I dishonored myself...
...when I gave my vows
to you in marriage.
You made a good marriage,
you're Caesar's wife!
I should have married a man
other than Caesar,
that would have been
a good marriage.
So I wouldn't have had to watch my husband
perform for Egypt every night,
in order to keep the riches
of that land flowing into Rome!
Between you and Cleopatra,
I don't know who is the concubine!
Retain your dignity, there's a limit
to what I'll hear from you.
I have no dignity left.
Perhaps... I ought to buy some.
Maybe I should learn, like you have,
that you can be bought and sold.
What's the price? What's the price
of consulship these days?
What's the price of being king?
When did your hope of bringing
a vision to the people...
...become this lust
for power itself?
Was it when Julia died?
I have nowhere else to go
so I'll stay here...
...but I'll live apart from you,
not as man and wife.
May the gods forgive me
for breaking my marriage vows,
as I pray they forgive you
for breaking yours.
You're an early riser, Brutus.
So are you.
Lately I am.
I couldn't sleep last night
worrying about the honor of your name.
Do you know something about these?
I know the writing,
but don't ask me who wrote them.
Minds change quickly
in these troubled times,
and I take you to forever
doubt these men.
Oh, Brutus I've done my best
to persuade them...
...that you are a man of honor,
though you wouldn't pledge
to keep Caesar from becoming king.
I gave you my pledge that
I'd oppose him in the Senate.
But some among us feel that to oppose
a man like Caesar with words...
...is the same thing
as handing him the crown.
I try to use words before
the sword, Cassius,
just as I try to use reason
before passion.
People say, calling on reason
before passion can lead to idleness,
and sometimes action is required.
But I know you're a decent man,
and that your meek and gentle nature
is how you feel you best serve the good.
I'm not gentle in
defending my beliefs,
but you have given me no proof
that Caesar will demand the crown.
Do you plan to be at the Senate
at the Calends of March?
No, I'll be here.
They say that on that day Caesar
will move that he be made king.
I will come if I am sent for.
This is what they mean.
People say that this is weakness,
to come when you are summoned
and at no other time.
To accept the favors
of a tyrant like Caesar.
- He spared my life!
- And he took the life of Cato...
...your wife's father,
who treated you like a son.
Has she ceased her mourning?
No, and neither have I.
- So you're grieving over Cato's death.
- Cassius, yes I'm grieving!
But private affection and public duty
are not the same thing.
And yet they say that in your grief,
you just weep and say prayers...
...and fill your wife's
drinking cup and go to bed...
...and when Caesar comes to you
tonight you'll be like his boy...
- ...and fill his cup as well.
- Oh, who is saying this? Who?
I don't act for Caesar!
I act for Rome! Always for Rome!
Brutus, I've done everything
to convince them...
...that you're a man of action
and that you love Rome.
I've spoken in your behalf many times
singing your praises...
...and condemning those
who speak against you, but...
...some men have ideas.
They think highly of those who gave
their lives to expel the kings from Rome.
Your ancestors!
And they were only men...
...not gods.
- Please don't stay.
- I am staying.
- Why do you want to torment yourself?
- I won't be tormented.
Will he?
Isn't that what you wanted to do?
It will be the best thing for Rome.
I don't trust that you or any other man
knows what's best for Rome.
I will take my seat.
A woman has a right
to see a bride, doesn't she?
Calpurnia!
Portia.
Romans, we're here to celebrate
the return of Caesar!
His return, not only with Her Majesty
Cleopatra, but with Egypt itself.
For he has transformed the richest land
in the known world.
It is now not only Egypt.
It is Egypt... and it is Rome!
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
I've said before...
...and I will say again:
I will not be king of Rome!
I an only Caesar!
I need no crown...
...to act on your behalf!
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
Do you still believe that ours
is not just cause?
I'm with you.
We have to act soon.
We will wait till Caesar
brings the Senate to order.
Lepidus will call for the elections.
Casca, you will ask Caesar
to consider the petitions first.
You, Cassius,
will step behind Caesar.
No man should go for his blade...
...until we're all within reach of Caesar.
Every knife must enter
Caesar's body...
...at least once.
And if... we fail,
or if our plot is discovered
before we even begin,
then we turn our knives on ourselves...
...without hesitation.
We all agreed?
Go to the Senate. I will meet
with Caesar at Cleopatra's house.
Go.
Brutus...
...why are you pacing like that?
I'm concerned we'll be late.
Caesar!
Calpurnia, what are you doing here?
I had a dream last night!
Please don't go out today!
I'll come to you later,
at our home.
I saw you slaughtered,
in your own blood!
It was horrible!
Well, I cannot let dreams
or flights of birds direct my actions.
I can't let you go. I swallow my pride
today to come to you,
because your life is more important to me
than my pride. Now you listen to me...
The Senate is convened for the consul.
They can't conduct one day
of business without their Caesar?
There are matters on the agenda...
...which can only be
dealt with by you Caesar.
- They can wait a day!
- And what should I tell the Senate?
That their consul is at home,
because his wife has had a bad dream?
As... your friend, Caesar,
I have to advise you on this.
You called the Senate together.
Show them you're a man of intention,
meet with your Senate.
They're waiting for your guidance.
I'll be with him lady.
I'll never leave his side.
I'll come to you later.
Hail, Caesar!
Portia.
I'm not fit to be alone today.
Sit down.
- Bring us some wine!
- Yes, let's have some wine.
What business do we have today?
Two legal briefings,
an election for a quaestor, and...
...the petitions from the Senate.
Let's get the election out of the way.
The election!
I move we...
...take the petitions, first.
I called for the election,
the election will commence.
But...
...Marcus Octavius, who is running
for the office, is not yet here.
Petitioners, then. Approach!
I'm glad Caesar is with Brutus today.
Why?
Last night I dreamt,
he was stabbed to death.
Brutus...
Caesar,
I ask mercy
for my exiled brother.
Why are you petitioning what
so recently has been denied?
Who is the next petitioner?
I want to ask mercy for my father,
who has been put in jail.
I ruled your father be
in prison and my word is law.
Old man!
You said something ill will befall
Caesar on the Ides of March.
Well, nothing has happened yet,
though the ides have come.
They have come,
but they've not yet gone.
I want to ask for your pardon,
my great Caesar.
And I pray for your soul.
Stop it!
Caesar!
Caesar has been slain!
Brutus...
AFTER CAESAR'S DEATH, ROME WAS PLUNGED
IN 15 YEARS OF CIVIL WAR
CAESAR'S KILLERS HAVEN'T SURVIVED
FOR MORE THAN THREE YEARS
NONE OF THEM DIED
OF NATURAL CAUSES
CASSIUS FELL BY THE SAME DAGGER
THAT HE HAD DIRECTED AGAINST CAESAR
BRUTUS TOOK HIS OWN LIFE
THE SAME WAY AS HIS UNCLE CATO
PORTIA LOST HER MIND OVER BRUTUS' DEATH
SHE KILLED HERSELF BY SWALLOWING HOT COALS
MARCUS ANTONIUS
AND CLEOPATRA FELL IN LOVE
WHEN AUGUSTUS, CAESAR'S SUCCESSOR,
TRIED TO CAPTURE HER, SHE COMMITTED SUICIDE.
THE SON OF CAESAR AND CLEOPATRA
MURDERED AT AUGUSTUS' COMMAND
CALPURNIA NEVER MARRIED AGAIN